the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to
perform I'm Dr Andy Galpin I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University
today we're going to be talking about
bone health and I wanted to cover this
for many reasons but first and foremost
is the fact that 50% of people out there
at some point in their life will break a
bone and so we want to do our best to
minimize that chance the likelihood of
us breaking our own bone but then on top
of that somewhere between 5 and 10% of
broken bones will not heal correctly so
after something has happened we want to
make sure that we're not in that 10% of
people so that our bones heal correctly
and as quickly as possible obviously the
more common and more frequent it is for
us to break bones the worse our health
is going to be having them not heal
correctly is going to lead to a whole
host of other short and long-term health
problems all right so why do you care
about this well people tend to think
about bone health and their mind at
least mine did initially jumps to things
like well this is only an issue for
older people and then really this is an
issue for older women for reasons I'll
discuss here shortly but that's not
necessarily the full story here there
are special things we need to pay
attention to especially for postmental
posit women but the reality of it is the
prevalence of poor bone health is
extraordinarily High across the globe in
men and women and it's rising at a rapid
rate there's some data that came out
recently suggesting that in 2007 the
prevalence of poor bone health here at
least in America was around
9% and that has risen to close to
133% again in the last decade alone on
top of all that is the fact that it is
what we call a silent disease so it is
unlike things like obesity or metabolic
issues uh brain health mental health
where you won't necessarily know what's
happening so part of the reason why bone
health is so poor in so many people is
because people have no idea there are no
signs there are no symptoms you don't
feel it you don't see it you don't hear
it until the bone breaks so it's really
common it's increasing and you probably
don't have any idea that it's happening
on top of all that it is extraordinarily
preventable so somewhere between 20 to
40% of your bone health is determined by
your lifestyle there are of course
genetic components filling in the rest
of the Gap there but you have a huge say
and the say is distributed across lots
of different options so that's the
foundation of what we're going to cover
today and let's jump right into it
today's episode is sponsored by element
element is an electrolyte drink mix that
has an ideal electrolyte ratio of sodium
potassium and magnesium but no sugar
hydration is critical to Performance
both physical and mental performance
countless Studies have shown that even a
slight degree of dehydration even as
small as 1% can lead to decreases in
physical output and mental performance
we also know that electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration which I've
been harping on for years but you can't
do that proper hydration by only
drinking water you need to get the right
amount of electrolytes in the right
ratios and that's why I'm a huge fan of
element in fact many of you will
probably remember that I featured
element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration nearly 5 years ago
I featured element in these videos
because they're blend of 1,000 Mig of
sodium 200 Mig potassium and 60 Mig of
magnesium really is unique and different
than any other electrolyte on the market
and it has great scientific support I
use element constantly particularly when
I'm sweating a lot and I routinely make
it a part of my client's optimization
programs if you'd like the try element
you can go to drink LM nt.com perform to
claim a free element sample pack with
the purchas of any element drink mix
again that's drink LM nt.com perform to
claim a free sample pack today's episode
is also sponsored by David David makes
protein bars unlike any I have ever
encountered they have an amazing 28 gram
of protein only 150 calories and Z gram
of sugar that's right 28 gram of protein
and 75% of its calories come from that
protein this is 50% higher than the next
closest protein bar honestly it's the
best tasting protein bar I've had by a
mile while I often talk about the
importance of getting 1 gram of protein
per pound of body weight for things like
muscle health and recovery and the
promotion of lean body mass and say tidy
the reality is that for most people
getting that 1 gram of protein per pound
of body weight is really challenging
however David makes that easy their bars
taste incredible and are each packed
with 28 g of protein I eat one almost
every day and always have two or three
in my backpack when I'm traveling like
literally always it probably sounds
funny but I eat them as dessert all the
time when you try them you'll know
exactly what I mean the macronutrients
one more time are 28 gam of protein 150
calories and 0 gam of sugar if you're
interested in trying these bars for
yourself you can go to
david.com perform again that's
david.com perform the first place I want
to start is basic terminology what
you'll hear in this field is three basic
things osteoporosis osteopenia and then
collectively poor bone health and so
very first the way that you want to
think about this is It's akin to
something like diabetes where you have
pre-diabetes and you have full diabetes
and diabetes would be collectively put
together as something like poor
metabolic Health that's essentially what
we're looking at so
osteopenia is this very first stop on
the journey to poor bone health
osteoporosis is now that full clinical
disease
uh which they both have technical
definitions officially osteopenia is one
standard deviation below the norm
osteoporosis is two and a half standard
deviations but the point is we're trying
to look at bone health as a progression
and saying hey we know that if you get
to technically osteoporosis your
prevalence and likelihood of breaking a
bone jumps astronomically and that then
leads to Shorter lifespan more suffering
and so on and so forth so let's stop
this problem before it happens and so we
can identify people that are clearly
along the path of low bone quality and
we'll call that osteopenia you smash
those things together and we now
collectively call it poor bone health
globally something like
40% of the population is in
osteopenia I mean let that thing sink in
40% of our population probably has
suboptimal bone health 20% probably
officially qualifies as osteoporosis
now in those over 5050 over 20% of women
have poor bone health so if you're
listening right now and you're a female
or you send this to a friend of yours
who's a female and 50 years old or older
there's a 20% chance you're actually
already an
osteoporosis good news is and we'll talk
about this shortly this can be improved
we can go backwards here and it is a
something we can potentially reverse but
it is really really common what I want
to focus on today is what do we do about
it we will of course cover the three
eyes that we are known for which means
we'll talk about how to investigate it
how do I measure it what should I be
asking for what should I be looking for
and paying attention to how do I
interpret those findings and then most
of our time today will be spent on the
third eye which is intervene what are
all of my options for either reducing my
likelihood of developing poor bone
health if I've already developed it how
do I reverse it and then if I have had a
break how do I accelerate proper healing
when we think about bones we tend to
think about them as the structural
component in other words they the thing
that keeps me up they're the thing that
keeps me moving and they you know keep
me alive that is true but I want you to
think about them more like body fat like
what do I mean here well if I were to
ask you about your body fat it provides
a little bit of structure it provides
some insulation it does those things but
the real true reason you have body fat
is so that you have backup energy
supplies in other words when you go into
a low energy State because you're moving
a lot or you're eating few calories you
will then take some fat out of the
stored tissue put it in your body and
use it in fact this is one of the
reasons why some people will store more
body fat than others because they're
particularly good at this preservation
mechanism bone has a similar property so
outside of the structural thing the
second most important thing that bone
does it it is your backup Supply but
instead of being for energy it's for
minerals and most specifically calcium
now why would I develop an entire
structure and system in my body just to
have a backup supply of calcium well go
back into season one of this podcast and
listen to the episodes on muscle
contraction and cardiovascular function
in that what you realize is all of
muscle requires calcium to contract your
skeletal muscle has to have it your
heart has to have it it is a critical
component to high quality fast and
successful muscle contractions if
calcium gets low in your body you will
die your heart will stop beating your
muscles can't contract but again you're
going to die because your heart stops
and so your body came up with a a very
unique and and and thoughtful way to
make sure you never ever ever under any
circumstances run out of calcium see if
you ran out of body fat you could
survive you could get energy from other
places and your liver and muscle stores
a little bit and so on and so forth you
have no options though if you run out of
calcium so what your body will do is it
will preserve muscle contraction and and
being alive quite frankly over top of
bone quality so when you get into a
situation when you don't have enough
calcium ingestion in other words you're
not eating enough or you're not
absorbing enough through your gut and
your internal calcium Supply start to
get low your body will turn to Bone and
start leaking it and pulling it out of
the bone and if this process continues
then therefore you lead to low bone
mineral density or low amounts of
calcium in your bones and you have
brittle bones and you're frail and they
break a lot that sucks but the reality
of it is that is better than you dying
and so that that uh hierarchy if you
will for calcium Supply is there on
purpose and so your bones are going to
pay the consequences of either poor gut
health poor nutritional status or other
rationale that would lead to that same
exact scenario so the first way we need
to frame this is poor bone health is in
some sense poor mineral health so we
have all these storage places in terms
of the minerals as I just mentioned
calcium is the big player here in fact
99% of the calcium in your body will be
stored in your bones some of it is in
your blood but this is usually because
it's being transported back and forth if
you were to look at your calcium levels
in your blood you from a traditional
blood test we can start to see insights
of your bone health now it's a little
bit tough for us to diagnose exactly
what's happening here because here's the
example if you're in a situation in
which you're intake or absorption of
calcium is low your body will recognize
this and it'll start pulling it out of
bone this will actually lead to a rise
or an increase in calcium concentrations
in your blood so if you're looking at
your blood work and saying wow my
calcium is really high I must be in a
great spot I have a ton of calcium it's
possible you're in the opposite
situation
this is potentially a sign of a poor
calcium status and so this is sometimes
confusing because people see this and
say things like hey my doctor told me to
take a calcium supplement but my calcium
numbers are really high in my blood this
doesn't make any sense this is what that
physician is potentially looking at and
saying it's high in the blood where it
shouldn't be because it's low in the
body if that little bit of backwards
math makes sense okay now in addition to
calcium there's a couple of other that
are going on in your bone from a mineral
perspective that we need to pay
attention to the next is phosphorus and
then magnesium now about 60% of your
magnesium in your body will be stored in
your bone so there are other things like
vitamin D in your bone in very small
amounts um but the the role of vitamin D
relative to bone health is not
necessarily because you need a lot of
vitamin D in your bone it's other things
if you don't have enough vitamin D uh
you'll get about a quarter of the
calcium absorption through your gut that
you would if vitamin D is sufficient
your bone cells actually directly do
have vitamin D receptors on them um so
there's actually another direct act you
have uh there it's also why like in the
1930s once scientists and Physicians
started realize what was going on with
rickets they started fortifying milk and
cereals and things like that with
vitamin D and you might be thinking in
fact to this day it's here in America at
least most of those products are still
fortified with vitamin D and that's
because those are a really high source
of calcium and if you if you coab orb
that vitamin D with that calcium you'll
get more of the calcium and that started
helping things like rickets because of
the vitamin D intake so if you're ever
wondering like why in the heck are all
my cereals and milk fortified with
vitamin D many reasons for that but this
is at least where that idea started with
okay so big minerals we want to pay
attention to calcium phosphorus
magnesium and another roll of vitamin D
here there's other things going on in
terms of a mineral like fluoride and
zinc and sodium potassium iron and
things like that but we're not going to
spend a lot of time talking about those
all that then to say and I mentioned
this a little bit earlier this is why
when we think of measures of bone health
we tend to use the phrase bone mineral
density or
bmd if you've ever had a bone scan if
you've ever heard people talk about it
and you wondered like why is actually
called mineral density that's what we're
looking at the more minerals in total in
your bone generally the more dense your
bone is the less brittle it will be the
less likely it is to break it's
generally considered to be healthier
those are not absolutes but you can see
the basic logic that's applied there if
your nutritional status or other things
are going on and you have to pull your
minerals from bone they become less
dense more likely to break and now we're
in that other side of the equation so
when we're talking about overall bone
health this is really what we're getting
at we need to have a lot of minerals
specifically calcium so that it can stay
dense and not break now your bones are
highly metabolically active again people
generally don't think about it they kind
of just get this idea that like my bones
are there they break or they don't break
but they're just moving me through space
they don't realize that they're there
for mineral deposition for the most part
they're also not realizing that they're
there for high metabolic activity so the
way that you'll hear this phrased is
bone remodeling or bone metabolism where
use them a little bit interchangeably
but this is happening constantly in fact
I remember thinking about this when I
first had my little kids but in the
first year of Life you'll 100% replace
your entire skeleton the turnover
happens really really rapidly but the
time you're an adult it's more like 10%
per year um somewhere in the
neighborhood like 5 to 10% of your bones
are being remodeled right now so it is
not a metabolically inert place it's
happening at a at an equivalent turnover
over of not the same but many other
systems like your skin and muscle and
things like that right so it's
constantly being remodeled now that
remodeling process is almost exclusively
responsible for short and long-term bone
health in other words if you develop
poor bone health you have low bone Minal
density and you have that because of
basic math problems you're either
breaking down too much bone or you're
not remodeling enough bone bringing in
new additional bone or some combination
of that
now that remodeling process is driven
almost
entirely by demand you'll hear this
called Wolf's Law but it's specificity
right when we talk about this from an
exercise or strength and conditioning
perspective we say a specific adaptation
to an imposed demand it's the said Sid
principle right so if you want to get
bigger biceps you lift with your biceps
if you want to get better at uh shooting
free throws you shoot free throws if you
want a lot of bone turnover you need to
challenge bone it is as simple as that
this is critically important because
this will directly explain what caused
the bad bone health and what we do to
solve the problem all right so the
specifics of how this remodeling work
ultimately tell us what intervention we
should go for now the way to think about
this is am I having a problem with too
much breakdown if so there are a
different set of interventions am I
having a problem with not enough
remodeling if so there's a different set
of interventions so hopefully that all
makes sense a little bit more detail
here and we'll get directly into some of
these examples this remodeling process
is regulated by a whole host of factors
but the two big ones are called Osteo
class and Osteo blast now Osteo means
bone and I'm going to be a little bit
annoying here just because I actually
remember being an undergraduate learning
about Osteo class an osal Blast for the
first time kind of dozing off a little
bit picking back up somewhere between in
the middle of the lecture and being like
wait did did she just say blast or class
and I would kind of like half pay
attention and then I would get
completely confused because the words
sound so much alike now if you're in a
classroom or you're watching this video
it'll probably be a little bit easier to
follow along with but if you're just
listening to the audio blast class blast
class blast class oh my God your your
your answering emails or your kid just
talked to you you're going to get
confused or potentially get confused so
in order do that I'll I'll be a little
bit annoying with this particular way
I'll describe him clas is with the C
Class think of clas as red right so when
you hear
class think red blast B with a B is
green so clast and blast red and green
now I don't like the connotation of the
colors there red is not bad classs are
not bad green is not the opposite but
let's pull those apart in your brain by
attaching them to a color okay now
osteoclasts the red ones are responsible
for breakdown just like in muscle muscle
breakdown is not bad bone breakdown
isn't bad you have to have it to remodel
you can't just add more on top of it
it's also the way we get rid of
dysfunction or breaks or problems in the
area right so we're cleaning house here
so osteoclasts lead to Bone breakdown
through a handful of mechanisms but the
basic principle here is it secretes a
bunch of acid on your bone they kind of
live in these little divots or grooves
that go along the outside of your bones
and when they get activated they secrete
a little bit of hyd hydrogen ions which
is acid onto the bone matrix it
dissolves it which releases the minerals
so step number one in remodeling or bone
metabolism is secrete that acid release
those minerals and that calcium into the
blood okay again it's not only happening
here just to remodel muscle but this is
just simply um it's kind of like the
bank teller opening up your Security
Vault there where you went in and said
we need some more money out we need some
more calcium and the bank tell says okay
great and opens up the door it's not a
negative thing they're just opening up
the door releasing some of this calcium
back in so classs red break it down
blasts B Green come in and do the
opposite where they're going to actually
secrete new bone they're going to start
off by making what's called type one
collagen um they're going to use
osteocalcin and alkaline phosphatase and
things like that which will come up a
little bit later but those things
provide the scaffolding that then you
can pour the calcium and the phosphorus
into that it can build around so the
two-step process breakdown class rebuild
with our blasts okay so again there's
different dysfunction different diseases
and different things that lead to an
accelerated or exaggerated activity of
our red clasps and some that suppress
our green
blasts right so then again one more time
our Solutions will depend on where the
problem is actually lying now I
mentioned earlier your lifestyle is
going to determine somewhere between 20
to 40% of your bone health and so what
are some of these actual factors that
happen that lead to accelerated bone
remodeling or bone metabolism well the
very first thing we want to think about
is that calcium intake and status and I
will double tap on that here pretty soon
other things that play a big role are
parathyroid hormone another one called C
tonin that actually comes from your
thyroid vitamin D as I mentioned
particularly when you're a kid you want
to be thinking about growth hormone
you'll often see this as a common
medical strategy for kids who are not
growing at a normal rate where they can
give them growth hormone to where they
can actually probably not accelerate and
be any taller than they would have been
but at least they can get to that
genetic potential rather than be stunted
there are other than things that are
what we'll call Bone derived cyto or
growth factors the big one that that
you'll hear commonly is called interlan
6 or I6 so there are many of other
things but this these are the big rocks
and so how this stuff can manifest
itself I gave you a little bit of the
calcium example earlier but this is
really what it looks like if you in the
case of low calcium status your body
will secrete a bunch of parathyroid
hormone now Osteo class this sees the
red ones don't have parathyroid hormone
receptors so it kind of works with this
indirect mechanism but it actually goes
to the blasts the blasts then secrete
things like interlan 6 which then turn
up or off the osteoclast so one way or
the other your body has realized we
don't have enough calcium it secretes
parathyroid hormone that then leads to
more calcium being put back into the
blood now this is fine if you have
enough in bone or your parathyroid isn't
going crazy if it's not being
artificially or otherwise pressed too
much so you could even be fine with your
calcium status but if you have issues
with thyroid or parathyroid it could
lead to problems like that I could give
a bunch more examples with the growth
hormone or caleton and other stuff but
we don't need to know them all what we
just need to realize is again
conceptually how this is working and why
my things like physical activity
metabolic health and nutritional status
why they're actually determining my bone
health with all that in mind unlike body
fat unlike skeletal muscle bone is
unique in the fact that by far by a
landslide and it's not even close the
most important thing you can do for bone
mineral density is to make sure you
reach your genetic normal Peak another
way to say this is the most common
reason for poor bone health as an adult
is because of not reaching bone mineral
density Peak as a child
you can do something about it in fact
when I was in school we were told you
can't these are recent findings that you
can actually do this but you still are
never going to reach probably where you
could have been had you not done it this
is often times why people will refer to
things like
osteoporosis as a childhood disease now
you will almost never be diagnosed with
osteoporosis until you're an adult
almost never until you're over the age
of 50 but they call it a childhood
disease because 10 the biggest thing
that caused you to have osteoporosis
when you were 60 was what you did
between ages 10 to 15 I don't want this
to come off the wrong way that doesn't
mean you can't do anything about it if
you are 50 with bad bone health you can
but we have to emphasiz high quality
bone health as a developing child or
we're always going to be chasing our
tail after that and this is exactly
why as a developing child you're
increasing both bone l length and Bone
mineral density you're growing right and
any of you that have had kids or been
around kids will will know this right
they'll shoot up in fact both of my kids
increased and grew three inches this
year almost identically right different
ages one boy one girl but they went up
by 3 Inches so you're getting longer
bones but by the time you've basically
finished puberty and those those growth
plates fuse your bones are as long as
they will ever be but your bone density
can continue to change
and so I'm going to give some numbers
here just to provide a little bit of
context okay the numbers themselves
don't matter a ton but so you can
conceptualize how big of a deal this is
right now the average man in terms of
the amount of grams how much bone you
total have on your body if we gave it a
number and called it, 1500 grams women
again on average May sit at something
like 1200 G so men are generally bigger
they have more total bone mass okay
that's great you're probably going to
reach that Peak Mass somewhere around 20
to 25 years old again for men let's just
call it 1500 Gams for women let's call
it
12200 after that men tend to hold on to
that bone mass pretty good for the next
10 to 20 years it'll start to slowly
decline around 50 years old or something
like that and by the time they hit say
90 or 100 they went from a total bone
mass of 1,500 gram to like a th right so
they they lost a third of their bone
mass over time with women it's
completely different so if you started
off at that peak of say 1
12200 you're going to start
declining around menopause and you might
go from 1,200 to 700 in a 5year span so
you see this just absolutely cataclysmic
drop and bone density during menopause
and then from there you'll still
continue to decline to where you're say
500 or less by the time you're the same
age as men and so we need to emphasize
bone health in men and women but we
really really need to emphasize that
women particularly during the menopause
window and that's why the vast majority
of the research and the funding and the
public advocacy has come with bone
health and women and it is completely
understandable but we actually have to
rewind the story because as I said while
your Peak bone will come and your 20s it
is directly explained by what you did in
the decade before so what do I mean by
this specifically about 40% of your bone
mineral density increases will happen
during your puberty range which is
usually like a 2 to threee window about
95% of what you're going to get into as
an adult is determined by what happens
during this short time frame so what
that really means is if at all possible
for girls ages 10 to 14 roughly you have
to really make sure that eating
reasonable quality I realize what that
sounds like for trying to get a teenage
girl to eat broccoli and things like
that but you got to do your absolute
best probably more important though and
the literature would support this is
exercise and movement for girls during
this time so whatever it takes to get
these young girls moving getting them at
least trying to eat pretty decent is
going to have implications for the next
60 to 80 years of their life the total
body bone mineral
changes per year are going to look
something like this for
girls say an average 9-year-old girl has
about a 50 g increase per year that's
going to five or six x over a couple of
year span so 9-year-old might have 50
grams per year that's being added to
their bone maral density by the time
they're 12 they're adding something like
30000 Gams per year and so you can just
see how this is going to multiply across
not only all of their bones but across
the years if their rate of increase
instead of being 300 gram per year that
they're adding is only 150 they're just
never going to get to that total Peak
that they need to get to for boys it's a
similar story but it's way less dramatic
instead of seeing these five or sixfold
increases in the rate of mineral growth
per year it's more like a doubling right
so they go from adding 100 grams a year
to 200 or 300 or something like that so
again it's important for both but it's
absolutely fundamental and critical that
we maximize bone mineral growth during
this range or this age for young girls
so hopefully by this point you've
realized the scope of the problem you
know what's exactly happening and now we
can start transitioning into how do we
measure these things how do we identify
where we're at and then what are the
different interventions today's episode
is sponsored by ag1 ag1 is a vitamin
mineral drink with probiotics prebiotics
and adaptogens initially I was extremely
skeptical of ag1 as I am with all
supplement companies but after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientist and the general team at ag1
I've been impressed by a1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts ag1
also rigorously test their products to
ensure that every single batch is free
of Bann substances allergens heavy
metals microbes pesticides herbicides
residual Sal an and mot toxins it's even
earned the prestigious NSF certified for
sport third-party testing approval stamp
now most people in the performance space
talk a lot about macronutrients like
protein carbohydrates and fats and these
are obviously critically important but
so are the micronutrients like vitamins
and minerals and even if you're eating a
healthy diet it's often hard to get
enough of these vitamins and minerals
along with the probiotics prebiotics and
adaptogens to keep your body performing
at its best it's for these reasons and
many others that I personally take ag1
almost every day now it's of course not
a replacement for eating whole healthy
foods but it is a great way to make sure
that you're plugging in any gaps in your
nutrition to improve your energy bolster
your immune system and just generally
help promote a healthy gut microbiome
and more if you'd like to try ag1 you
can go to drink a1.com perform to
receive five free travel packs plus a
year supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 again
that's drink a1.com perform to receive
five free travel packs plus a year
supply of vitamin D3 plus K2 if you were
to look across the scientific landscape
you would find about nine different
factors that globally go into people
having poor bone health I broke them up
into what I call modifiable and
non-modifiable the non-modifiable ones
are there's just two of them and I'm not
going to spend much time on them because
you can't do much about it the first is
actually things like genetics there's a
big component to that Earth we've talked
about that number and so great moving on
past that the second non-modifiable one
has historically been age as I discussed
earlier men and women seem to lose bone
mineral density especially from 50 years
old and on and that is just sort of
thought to be a part of life that said
there have been significant and serious
challenges to this thought so much so
that I actually think that I can make
make a decent argument to take this off
the list entirely what I'm saying is
there is this classic thought of being
regardless of what you do you'll just
lose bone Minal density because you're
getting older but now some more recent
research has indicated that the loss of
physical activity that happens with
aging directly explains the reduction of
bone mineral density such as to say if
you were to Simply keep your physical
activity at the same level you might not
lose bone moral density just because
you're getting older the only set
exceptions to this are things like
menopause now what happens with
menopause as people are mostly aware of
is women's uh concentrations of estrogen
go down dramatically and often times
pretty quickly estrogen keeps
osteoclasts the red ones in check so
when the estrogen goes away those classs
run kind of unmitigated and unmanaged
and so bone breakdown happens at a
really high rate so if we're looking at
interventions for post menop positive
women one of our first stops on this
journey is how do we reduce osteoclast
activity rather than even worrying too
much about what's happening with the
blast we just have to slow these classs
from again running wild same thing
actually happens in men it's not called
menopause we often call it
andropause um and that's when that has
that that large drop in testosterone now
it's actually something that people
don't really realize is uh the
testosterone estrogen kind of follow the
same path in men so when we see this big
drop in testosterone we also see a drop
in estrogen for men this is why their
bone menal density can go down as well
especially if they have a large
pronounced drop in testosterone for any
number of reasons it's not nearly as
pronounced as women but it does happen
there so I will give you those ones are
I don't I don't think we can make an
argument that menopause only happens
because you stop being active or
anything like that um I'm not not aware
of any ability to stop menopause from
happening and I'm not sure you wouldd
want to even do that so these ones I
will give you but the age in general I
will I will argue again against and
hopeful for more research to come out
soon on that but those factors we would
generally call either non-modifiable
entirely or minimally modifiable the
modifiable ones I'll call the big seven
the first one we'll talk about is
actually what are collectively called
environmental toxins now you can bucket
these into three big categories the
first ones are the heavy metals the most
common ones uh aluminum Mercury lead
cadmium kind of fall into this category
now the next Cate are what we generally
call chemicals things like bpas Fates um
antibacterials pesticides and things
like that and then category three are
air pollutants so particulates nitric
oxides sulfur dioxides ozon and and
things like that I'm not going to get
any more in just in the sake of times
into these environmental toxins I would
recommend you go check out a great
episode of The hubman Lab podcast where
Andrew covered a lot of environmental
toxins and microplastics and things like
that and so you can go learn more about
this General category there but again
for the sake of wanting to focus on the
interventions we're going to move on
past environmental toxins for now the
next big categor to the second of our
big seven are what I'll just call
diseases and these are things like
metabolic disease there is a well
documented relationship between diabetes
and hyperthyroid and bone meral density
so I just collectively call those things
metabolic diseases you'll see the same
thing actually more recently for gut
health disease dises celiac disease and
IBS also have a documented negative
influence on bone mineral health and
then another category that people all
don't talk about very often and also
covered pretty recently on the huberman
Lab podcast is oral health there is a
really strong connection between not
only the health of your teeth but how
your oral health will influence whole
body uh bone health and so you can again
see more of those things later so number
one was environmental toxins number two
were Collective group of diseases number
three are what I call drugs and
medications alcohol and smoking fall
into this category I don't think I need
to stretch your imagination to realize
those are generally bad for everything
and of course then they're bad for bone
a more controversial one that I'll tread
lightly on here are things like caffeine
and specifically uh Cola and really what
I'm talking about is is the long
argument about how caffeine and sodas
whether they diet or not in influence
bone health particularly in kids um you
can dive into that hornest Nest as much
as you'd like but I think most of us
would agree at this point copious
amounts excessive amounts of those
substances particularly caffeine in kids
is not good for bone health but the ones
that people are be a little bit more
surprised about um that are not in the
medical community are things like
gastric reflux medications now this
probably is ringing some Bells cuz I
just said earlier about how things like
IB s and CX disease are connected to
bone health and then I talked about even
earlier than that how there's various
gut health protocols we can go through
to help bone maral density so you're
seeing a pretty strong connection here
between altering various aspects of our
gut microbiome and bone health the other
one that people are often really
surprised at are the cortical steroids
so prazone being the most well
documented one most Physicians are very
aware of this but the general population
is not there is an incredibly strong set
of
literature unfortunately showing a
connection between prazone
use and Bone mineral loss so you want to
be really careful about again any
cortical steroid but prednizone really
has a documented negative effect on bone
health so always make the best medical
decision for you based on a number of
factors it's always a choice don't let
me help you decide what you do for your
medicine nor your physician you to work
that out how you want to deal with it
but something to really pay attention to
okay so in terms of our big seven that
is drugs and medications are the third
category the fourth one is sedentary
Behavior or lack of physical activity
I'm going to hammer you with this a
little bit later so we're going to move
past it right now and get into the fifth
category which is
malnutrition the three big things you're
going to jump out from Mal nutrition's
perspective are things like being
underweight and anorexia
you should be able to make some leaps of
Faith here with saying things like okay
if I'm missing vitamin and mineral
nutrient intake because of simply not
having enough calories that's going to
affect bone mineral health and that is
exactly what happens at this point so
from a micronutrient perspective the
vitamin D and calcium U magnesium zinc
Boron copper also highly Associated uh
with poor bone health if they don't come
in sufficient amounts and then the other
one that will pop up the most in
literature is a really bad Omega 6 to
omega3 ratio right so these are your
your your your fish oils if you will and
Seed oils and things like that just
making sure that ratio is reasonable and
not making sure the Omega sixes get
really really really high especially in
the presence of low Omega-3s um that
will have a pronounced impact on bone
health Okay the third one in this
category so outside of just being
underweight and or combination of
micronutrient insufficiencies or
deficiencies here is high acidity right
now you should be able to go back and
say ah okay I remember the way that OC
class the red ones work is they secrete
a bunch of acid onto bones and that
breaks them down therefore if I'm in
this continuous Perpetual highly acidic
environment it'll probably have a
similar effect and in turn it actually
does that and so making sure that we're
not being in this Ultra acidic
environment from a nutritional
perspective is another thing we can do
to pay attention to make sure that our
bone heeld
stays where it needs to be so those are
the first five we want to tackle the
next two are chronic stress and bad
sleep and so let me talk about those
things
independently chronic stress if you look
at the research on things like anxiety
and depression and PTSD you'll see a
strong correlation between those and
poor bone health now that's just
correlation what's the mechanism what's
causing it there's a lot of stuff I
could talk about here but I'll give one
tangible example that I think most
people will resonate and connect with
and these are things that I'll globally
call cortisol dysfunction now I'm not
really a supporter of adrenal fatigue
but cortisol dysfunction is a very real
thing there are actual diseases like
Cushing's Disease and this highlights it
really well so Cushing disease is a
basically it's a cortisol disease there
have been studies finding reporting that
80% of people with
cushions have poor bone health
in fact over 50% of them have actual
osteoporosis now we know osteoporosis is
really common in the general population
but it's not this common so clearly just
looking at that relationship saying
people that have cortisol dysfunction in
this disease State at a really high rate
have poor bone health so potentially
there's something happening well what do
we know happens we know that cortisol
will inhibit Osteo blast activity so the
B the green ones it'll block the
formation of new oste oo blasts from
stem cells and it promotes osteoblast
apoptosis so it makes the blast you have
not work it makes you not be able to
create new ones and it makes the ones
that you currently have die on top of
that cortisol also stimulates and
activates osteoclasts the red ones it
then further promotes calcium release
and also blocks calcium absorption so it
has a bunch of different mechanisms in
which you can alter bone quality
now as always when we talk about
anything that has a hormetic stressor
and cortisol being one of the ones
people tend to pop up with it's the most
in then in the Lexicon it people hear
about it they blame it a lot it's not
all negative this is a really good thing
to happen in short high bursts why this
stimulates bone turnover this keeps your
bones healthy this is what allows you to
have high quality tissue it allows you
to put minerals into your system this is
a great thing the problem always with
cortisol and the problem always with
stress and the problem always with
hormetic stressors are when they're at a
low to moderate level chronically so you
can imagine doing something like
exercise where it releases a huge amount
of cortisol really fast stimulates this
growth stimulates turnover and goes back
down to Baseline
however if it's persistent for a long
amount of time and you're continually
blocking these blasts and continually
accelerating these classs then we're
going to eventually lead to low bone
density overall so this is just one
example how something like a
psychological stressor could lead to a
physical consequence and in this case
directly contributing and causing poor
bone
health obviously anytime we bring up
cortisol the reality it is things get
much more
complicated than what I just described
but I think this highlights just one
area of how we could think about Stress
Management and your doctor trying to
tell you hey you got to get your stress
under control and you're thinking like
well how's that affecting my bones this
is one way or in fact many of how that
could be
happening now part and parcel to that
often times in combination with
chronically high stress is bad sleep
they don't have to both be there but bad
sleep has a really really negative
effect on bone health there's this is
actually coming out really recent in the
last couple of years there's been a
handful of really big randomized control
Trials come out in fact one particular
paper I want to highlight titled sleep
disruptions and bone health what do we
know so far did a really nice job of
laying this out but this is a really
deep large landscape of literature
there's a really clear differentiation
between those who sleep less than 5
hours per night and those that sleep 7
hours per night or more you're talking
about an odds ratio of
1.22 for low bone mass versus 1.6 for
osteoporosis and you can kind of think
about this as like a almost a 63%
increase in risk of developing
osteoporosis it doesn't mean you have a
63% chance of developing it but your
risk has gone up by 60 plus percent if
you're sleeping and insufficient amount
so Total Sleep duration is right out the
gates leads to a lot of problems okay
now it does this a lot of different ways
but one of the things that's been
learned more recently are things that
are called clock genes now these are a
whole host of genetic influences
relative to things like not just total
sleep but circadium disruptions so this
is sleeping at irregular times this is
sleeping at irregular schedules this is
night work or night or shift work or
things like that right disturbing your
circadian clock independent of time now
we know these clock genes have existed
for long long time but what's only been
shown recently is that they have a
direct influence on bone cells and so
this part of the mechanism story was
never around before we're like we know
that hey bad sleep is bad and then like
all things that are generally bad for
your health gender contribute to
everything else but the direct discovery
of these clock genes in bone cells was a
huge breakthrough of understanding that
the mechanisms by which this happened
all right now the way that this happens
and you can actually Intuit it a little
bit of here is we know that there's dial
variations and Bone turnover markers
which is to say the amount of bone
turnover happening in the morning is not
the same that's happening at night right
that it changes throughout the day and
we knew that we also knew that that was
happening in concordance to circadian
rhythms and so now having those clock
genes as the direct or one of the least
the direct explanations there tied that
story together okay so sleep duration is
a problem to pay attention to and sleep
circadium rhythm is also something to
pay ATT attention to so to summarize all
that up there are seven in my opinion
big categories of modifiable factors
that lead to poor bone health those big
seven were environmental toxins a
collective range of different
diseases various drugs and medications
physical activity or sedentary Behavior
malnutrition or poor nutrition chronic
stress and then finally bad sleep at
this point hopefully you've learned a
lot about how Bones Work what they
really are how they're playing a role in
multiple areas of your physiology not
just hard things that are inert and
carrying your bag of cells throughout
this entire world hopefully I've also
convinced you to pay more attention to
them in fact what I just covered is a
lot of things that you'll need to do or
want to do to maximize your overall bone
health you don't actually need to get
anything tested if you want to just take
advantage of those seven modifiable
areas but that said some of you are
still going to be interested in directly
testing your bone mineral health and I
would encourage you to do that and so
I'm going to lay out really quickly what
your options are across a range of
accessibility and costs starting right
out the gates you can actually learn a
lot completely free there are a number
of options you can do there is what's
called a Frack
FX it's a fracture risk assessment tool
I actually have directly linked one uh
to you in the show notes you can go you
can enter a bunch of information there
and it will give you your 10year
fracture probability obviously anytime
we're using a questionnaire and not
direct testing or imagery that we're
going to lose some accuracy but this is
scientifically validated in fact if you
look around you will see the fq the
Frack used all over the place it's
extraordinarily common in bone health
rather if you can though whether you're
paying cash or you can get medic uh your
insurance to cover it hopefully you have
accessibility to it what you're probably
looking at here in terms of imagery is
What's called the dexus scan now this is
often abbreviated as D XA or just simply
dxa most of the general recommendations
are going to tell you that if you're a
woman over age 65 or you're a man over
age 70 that you should just get a dexa
scan regardless I am way more aggressive
in this though as I told you at the very
beginning the reason is I have
personally uh put people through and and
ordered hundreds of dexas scans athletes
non-athletes our male clients our female
clients across my personal coaching
programs and a lot of the times we see
people come back who are generally
healthy they're lean they're active
they're doing a bunch of stuff they're
young and they still have really low or
poor bone quality and so I I think that
if if you consider the cost you're
generally looking at somewhere in the
neighborhood of1 to $300 us for a DEA
scan again most of the time your
insurance will cover it if you're a
30-year-old you might have a hard time
getting insurance to cover it sometimes
you know 100 bucks is just not even
possible for you but if it is a lot of
people can get their way to you know1
$150 to get one of these scans and so I
actually honestly recommend people
getting this as soon as they possibly
can certainly by the time you're 40 I
think men and women should have this
because if you can catch this uh imagine
you're a woman and you have not gone
through menopause yet and you have no
idea you're kind of Physically Active a
little bit maybe you've gone through
spurts you've worked out then you kind
of fell off the train you're back in a
little bit you eat pretty well but not
tremendous you might already have
osteopenia perosis you could also be
great but if you are even okay or
slightly low and then you get that known
dip that comes with menopause you could
be in in pretty serious issues here
where if you had five or 10 years to
accelerate your bone quality before the
menopause hit this is massively changing
your life so for all these reasons I
think it's actually personally I would
recommend getting it a lot sooner
earlier in life um then 65 to 70 I think
that is I would would be willing to bet
those numbers are going to change
recommendations are going to start
coming way down to scanning way earlier
in
life but me personally if at all
possible if you live in a region where
you have access to these things which
they're all over the place and you could
possibly afford it I would recommend
this as a very low risk a fairly cheap
and a high potential quality result that
being said you also have other options
in terms of Imaging if you really think
you have osteoporosis or osteopenia you
can't get that diagnosed with a normal
dexus scan so for example when I order
this for the people I work with we're
generally just looking at total bone
mineral density which is not what's
going to qualify for osteopenia or
osteoporosis so we order this and we're
looking at body composition total mass
and various things like that if your
physician really thinks you're at risk
for some of these things or you are
concerned about it then you actually
need to order a different scan that's
more specific to the pelvic region the
hip region the lumbar region and things
like that that's for some technical
official reasons but I'm saying that
because again having had many clients go
through these and come back and they go
oh my God I have osteopenia I'm like
whoa you don't have osteoporosis yet we
need many other pieces of information to
fill that in but it's nice starting
place it's a flag if you go through a
normal dexas scan that are available
again kind of everywhere and you do see
numbers that are poor which I'll cover
in one second then that might lead you
to go to your doctor and say hey I got
this inial scan now I actually want to
see if if I can get checked out for
osteopenia if I have it so I want I
don't want you to over interpret dexus
scans that way now the dexas have been
around for a long time but there are
some emerging technologies that look to
offer some really unique solutions that
dexa has always been limited by the one
that pops out the most is called
qct This is called quantitative computed
tomography don't worry about all that
but basically it allows you to go in and
individually look at bone segments and
so when you generally get a Dexter scan
you're going to get this total body
score and the way that it works is
you're going to lay on a machine it's
going to shoot some um some things up
through the bottom of your body and it's
going to try to connect those to the the
Imaging part of the machine on the top
which is a way to say they're not
actually giving you bone meral density
they're just kind of giving you like a
2D image and then estimating
circumference and diameter and area
around that well this qct stuff allows
actual volumetric density so it's going
to come in different units like
milligrams per centimeter cubed rather
than squared if you have no idea what
I'm talking about there don't worry
about it if you're
math uh an efficient Auto you're going
to be like oh wow I I picked up on what
he said there but you can get a whole
bunch of B midal density uh uh
specificity that we can't right now get
on dexa most of us though are going to
use that dexa scan a lot of people have
already had this and they really had no
idea the dexa and Bone Minal density is
notoriously uh difficult to interpret
I'll say a lot of times you get it back
and maybe they've colorcoded it for you
and you got a green so you're like great
that's good or it's red so you think
it's bad but uh it's not an intuitive
response where something like this is
how much muscle you have this is your
body fat people are kind of comfortable
with those numbers
the bowal density results come back in a
very confusing fashion so let me break
it down for you really quickly how do
you interpret these results well first
of all if you're going in to get a dexa
scan generally you're going to see just
that total body number if it's more
advanced and depending on the scan that
the operator selected ideally you get
things like your lumbar spine your total
hip your femoral neck and then your
actual forearm if you can have those
individually isolated that is
advantageous and that is what a
physician again would look at if they're
trying to truly diagnose osteopenia
osteoporosis but nonetheless those
scores are going to come back and you're
going to see it represented as two
things well three things total you know
density if you will but it's going to be
not given to you in like a number but
it'll be given to you in what's called a
t score and a z score okay now T scores
are going to come almost always if you
are a postmenopause male or female over
the age of 50 right and why they do that
is they're going to say the t- score
represents your value and density
relative to a young healthy person so if
you're 50 what is your bone density look
like relative to a 22-year-old of the
same sex and the same ethnicity so the
way that this is reported back to
you is in the format of something like
this if your score is greater than -1
then you are in the upper 15th
percentile and you probably just heard
all that and just said like what the
hell did he just say Okay
so t-core is relative to the 22-year-old
best version of yourself theoretically
if you were at a score of zero that
means you're the exact same score well
that's awesome because you means now
theoretically again as an example here
you have the same bone health or quality
or density as a 55-year-old as you did
when you were 20 that would be
tremendous right CU it's supposed to go
down with age if the score is like one
or one and a half that means you have
more than the average person you're age
and sex and and ethnicity which would be
great in fact even if it's a little bit
negative negative .5 negative 1 that
still puts you in the top 15 percentile
okay so again a little bit weird to say
but a score of higher than negative 1 so
negative 1 to zero or even literally
positive is the the best possible score
here if you score somewhere between that
Nega -1 and
-22 now you're in what's called
osteopenia so that is actually the
definition the one by the way is one
standard deviation the two and a half is
two and half standard deviations from
that Norm so 85 percentile or higher for
the top scor you're in the 14% of people
are going to be in this osteopenia thing
and if you're more negative than -2 and
a half so more than two standard
deviations away then you are now
considered osteoporosis pretty much full
stop the risk of a broken bone
increases about doubles actually per
point on your t-core so if you go from a
negative one to a -2 you've basically
doubled your risk of breaking a bone if
you go from a negative2 to neg3 you've
doubled it again the zcore is more like
U to you right so if you you're going to
get if you're younger by the way you may
not get a t score at all so if you're
like a 25y old a 35y old you might just
straight have gotten this t- score
because it's like what's the point of
giving you a zcore when you're already
that age right so again if you're over
50 or 55 you'll get a zcore and a t
score but if you're younger than 50 you
might just get this zcore so the zcore
is how do you score relative to the same
person your age that's what it means
again your age your sex your ethnicity
and so again if you're zero you're
neutral if you're one that means you're
one standard deviation above the person
if you're less than it's the same it's
the same scoring criteria right so
negative -1 to 2 and a half to two and a
half all the way down so someone greater
than -2 means you know you're you're
pretty significantly lower than where
the average person is your age in terms
of actual numbers I I wanted to throw
this in as well you guys know how I
always like to put in kind of World
Records when I can the highest I found
in the literature from an absolute
perspective most men are going to be
somewhere between 1.1 to 1.2 gr per
centimeter squared again we're not
talking t zcore or t score here we're
talking about Absolute Total number here
one to 1.1 to 1.2 is normal I did find a
study that reported people at
1.7 which would you know your your t
score would probably be like five at
that point like I don't know that's
really really high up there right um
women are generally about 1.1 so it's a
little bit lower than men and again I'm
talking about men and women their 20s
right now for the most part cuz that's
that's where you're going to be your
Peak right and the highest female number
I came across was 1.5 I would love to
know anyone out there if you've ever
seen any papers published with higher
numbers than that um but if you're ever
looking at your scores and you want to
know like I'm good but how good am I
those are the metrics to go after for a
man if you get above 1.7 I'll be
impressed for women you get above 1.5 at
any age I'll be pretty impressed as well
but that said for the average person how
do we contextualize these scores a
little bit better well you want to think
about this in terms of progression more
than almost anything from a t-core
perspective remember t-score is you
relative to that standard young healthy
person if you are going through an
intervention and you are looking at your
t-core and you're trying to make some
change and then six months later you get
it measured again what you want to see
is that t- score may or may not improve
but you don't want it to go down if it
is holding tight what that's actually
meaning is you're improving so it's a
little bit of math trick there but
that's really what you want to see so
when we don't see you know increases in
the t- score I don't get super concerned
about it because it is relative to that
age person and you've gotten older now
so a t-core of the same is actually
meaning that your bone is holding on
which is great because remember most
people's bone is going down so the fact
that you're maintaining is itself a gain
it's progress right um the total
concentration is something we would look
at if we're getting that on a report if
our total concentration is going up then
we know we're going the right direction
even if our t score is not the zcore
though the U relative to youu at the
same age should be improving so a little
bit
um help to pay attention to how to
interpret those things when you get your
results back last thing I'll say about
this is in terms of how frequently you
test every six months is probably pretty
good if you want to actually do it every
year I'm okay with that bone turnover is
slow so that's what we should be paying
paying attention to that's what we
should test that's how we should test it
that's how we should interpret it now
let's talk about how do we do something
about it how do we intervene what do we
know what should we do how much it's
going to work and how should I employ it
today's episode is sponsored by momentus
momentus makes the highest quality
supplements on the market period many of
you know me and you know that I do not
trust the vast majority of supplement
companies and for a good reason many
Studies have shown that anywhere between
10 to up to 40% of supplements have
accidental contam amance intentional
alterations mislabeling or other serious
issues but momentus is different I
literally spent years vetting the
company their products and leadership
team before personally officially
partnering with them in 2023 every
single one of moment's products is
thirdparty tested to ensure quality and
many are even NSF certified for sport
now while I love all of their products
the ones I use the most both personally
and with my clients are what I call the
big three and these are the omega-3 fish
oil creatine and newly improved whey
protein formula these three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits and they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people young old men
women Etc now nobody has to use
supplements and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so but if you're
interested in supplements it's important
that you get them from the highest
quality providers so that's why I stick
exclusively to momentus if you'd like to
give momentus a try go to liv.com
perform to get 20% off your order again
that's liv.com perform to get 20% off
today's episode is also brought to you
by Renaissance periodization if you want
to put on muscle through science-backed
training programs look no further than
renaissance periodization renaissance
periodization guides users through
effective and easy to follow strength
training programs all through their
hypertrophy app these programs are
designed by the absolute best in the
industry including one of my favorite
sports scientists and professional
bodybuilders Dr Mike Israel you may
recognize that name because I reference
him and his work countless times over
the years whether you're looking to put
on muscle gain strength or both these
programs will help you achieve your
goals and have produced results in
thousands of men and women Renaissance
periodization also has a diet app that
is backed by the latest science and
innovation in the field of nutrition and
takes the complexity out of dieting
helping you achieve your ideal body
composition if you'd like to try
Renaissance periodization go to
rpstrength tocom perform to save up to
$50 off your subscription again that's
rpst strength.com perform to save up to
$50 off of your subscription there's a
necessary caveat I need to talk about
here and it's always true but
particularly relevant for bone health
it's what I call the evidence versus
action Continuum the way you want to
think about this is for you in your
personal scenario how much evidence do
you need to see before you take action
and I'm saying it this way because it is
different for everyone if you on the
individual level are trying to improve
your bone health you may not require as
much evidence for things to have as much
of an impact a lot of people have the
philosophy of saying like hey if it's
not dangerous or negative and there's
many things I can do I want to do as
many of them as possible even if they
have a small impact and that's up to you
to decide where somebody who's maybe a
medical physician might say hey there's
not enough evidence for me to recommend
it medically or there's evidence that it
but it doesn't have a huge impact
therefore I'm not going to give it a
medical recommendation that's maybe a
different barrier and then even higher
up that is things like insurance
coverage so what they might want to see
in terms of evidence for either quality
of evidence amount of evidence or effect
is almost surely different than what you
might want to see on the individual
level really important that we that we
go over that right now because we're
just not going to see the same level of
impact on bone that we see in other
common areas it would not surprise me to
see somebody improve muscle mass by 10%
in a few months or to lose 40 or 60 or
80 pounds you're not going to see
somebody double their bone Minal density
or you're just not going to see numbers
like that and so we have to really shift
what we think is actionable or
non-actionable or worth it when it comes
to changing and improving bone mineral
Health you will see this is treated
medically a lot of different ways with a
lot of positive benefits right there are
estrogens there are serms not sarms but
serms um the most common one by far are
what are called bif phosphinates right
so biosas are super common it's by far
the most recommended medication for bone
health it slows down burn turnover or a
bone turnover rather by forcing those
osteoclasts the red to undergo apoptosis
so remember earlier when I said hey when
you start going through menopause
estrogen crashes and the biggest thing
that that causes is because they're
keeping those classs in check that those
classs run wild and so it makes total
sense from a medical perspective then
you know independent of treating
estrogen which you may or may not be
doing to Simply give you a drug that
stops those Osteo class and this is what
those bif phosphinates do so really
effective really well demonstrated and
again used really really really commonly
the problem with it is not everyone
wants to take medications not everyone
has access to these things they're
pretty expensive they have a a pretty
well documented history of drawbacks and
so I don't want you to dissuade you away
from taking them certainly again I'm not
a medical doctor at all and I'm
certainly not your medical doctor by any
stretch so make the best decision that
you see fit with your physician and so
on and so forth but I'm only saying that
to say right now I want to actually talk
about all the other options so for the
people that don't want the medications
can't use them are having the side
effects what other things do we know
about but I couldn't cover interventions
without talking about the most common
most effective and welld demonstrated
one which is of course these various
medications so that said in my
particular opinion the best things we
can do for bone health are the following
get it as good as you possibly can as a
kid particularly during those 3 to four
years during puberty I said that earlier
but I will probably I would like to say
it 50 more times before we're done today
that's how critical this stuff is we're
really talking about nutrition but a
especially talking about movement
exercise physical activity whatever
phrase you want to give it you got to
move as a kid you got to move during
puberty but let's be more specific
physical exercise specifically
resistance exercise in kids as clear as
I can say this does not stunt growth
plates lifting weights in kids will not
hurt bone menal density it will not make
them get shorter it will not fuse those
end plates any sooner or anything like
that I I can't emphasize enough how much
I want to kill the absolute hell out of
that myth we have known this answer for
a long time and somehow it continues to
persist around the world it is
absolutely and fundamentally untrue in
fact very
specifically many many studies over tens
of thousands of kids generally strength
training resistance training weight
training Plyometrics enhance bone
quality and most importantly not only
does it do it in that age window it will
last then the rest of their life
remember earlier when I said what you do
as a teenager will determine your bone
maral density the rest of your life this
will happen as well with exercise
strength training resistance exercise
Sports and everything else like that so
these things are good for kids in
general
obviously within range I don't want you
to overuse kids burn them out you can do
too much physical activity like all
those things are true right we're
talking about is responsible exercise
supervised strength training making sure
kids are playing and still having fun
and all of the necessary caveats that
should be there of course kids can get
hurt when they lift weights of course
you can do damage but in general these
things are not only okay and safe
they're incredibly productive for short
and long-term bone health I can't be
more clear on on that point there is
evidence that simply being active kids
that are Physically Active think about
this in terms of a study where you
simply ask kids about how active they
are what does active mean whatever they
want it to mean okay so just being
active over 90% of studies that have
been done in this area find positive
benefits with activity and bone maral
density it doesn't matter if we're
looking at randomized control trials
intervention studies cross-sectional
longitudinal questionnaires retroactive
studies you smash them all together 90%
of them find positive associations
between more active and more bone
mineral density again obviously that can
be taken to an extreme where you're too
active but you get the point here
right very directly active kids between
the ages of 8 and 15 will have 10% more
bone mineral density by the time they're
in their 20s and 30s 10% more when
they're more active between age 8 and 15
so again you're really laying the
foundation for what they're going to
deal with the rest of their life the
benefits that we see with physical
activity seem to be accelerated more
specifically with sport interaction and
it's actually by a large margin
somewhere between like 10 to 16% of the
difference in bone mineral density in
kids who play sports versus those who
don't so if I were to take kids that are
generally playing sports versus kids at
the same age that are not playing sports
we would expect again a 10 to 16%
increase or greater amount of bone ra
density in those kids playing sports so
keep your kids active get them playing a
lot of different sports and activities
if then on top of that as a third area
you want to add in what I call formal
exercise then that's great this is when
you're intentionally exercising
intentionally having them uh lift
weights or intentionally doing things
like that that's great but the reality
of it is I firmly believe if your kids
are active and playing again a very open
definition of sport that's probably
going to be everything that you need the
one thing I will emphasize here
is most of the research and most of the
benefit tends to come from jumping and
Landing remember Wolf's Law in order for
a bone to increase or to be stimulated
you got to place a large Demand on it
you need actual structural pounding of
the of the bone itself or you need the
muscle to be contracting at a rate where
it's really ripping on the bone not a
slow cont controlled contraction right
so either the weight itself has to jar
up and down and called create axial
loading on the bone to stimulate it or a
muscle or a tendon or connected tissue
has to be directly pulling on it rapidly
and aggressively so most of the studies
here are plyometric based which is
further emphasizes our Point Plyometrics
themselves are not dangerous for kids in
fact they're generally very beneficial
you've gotten the point by now let's go
ahead and move on what do we know about
exercise
after this puberty right so now we're
generally thinking I've gotten into my
20s 30s or more and I'm now I got low
bone density how do I get it back up
what do we know well exercise studies
still work the magnitude of effect is
smaller to be totally honest it's
generally still statistically
significant and clinically meaningful
but the numbers you're going to see
there are somewhere between like 3 to
2% which is again crazy if I told you
this six months intervention gave you a
half a percent increase in strength
you'd be like oh that sucked but a half
a percent increase in bone is like yay
that that's great we're super happy
there right while the boneal density
effect is smaller you start to add on
other things right think about all the
countless benefits of exercise that
you're getting from any other variable
but in this thing you start now getting
balance and you start getting a
reduction in Falls so there is a
significant reduction in your likel of
having a fall when you exercise you're
not going to break your bone if you
don't fall and so you're kind of
actually keeping your bones healthier
from two sides of the equation now the
bone itself as well as reducing the
likelihood of putting your bone in a bad
position it is very very clear hopefully
I made this argument that just being
physically active as a kid is is enough
you can get there you don't have to lift
weights you don't have to play sports if
you're active enough you're jumping and
playing and doing things like that as a
kid you're probably fine as an adult
though it's not the same story
unfortunately almost surely at this
point you're going to have to go out of
your way to strength train as an adult
let's start off by remembering the
mechanism Wolf's Law stress is we're all
about stress here causing
adaptation where we get thrown off here
is it's not the actual load that matters
it is the change in load so if you are
not used to lifting weights at all if
you never run if you don't do anything
that puts a huge impact on your bone if
you get a little impact on your bone
that's enough to stimulate growth
however if you're already at a
reasonable amount of loading you have to
do more than you've currently been doing
to stimulate bone growth it is the
change it is the altering from
homeostasis that signals it not the
actual load itself and this part is
critical because what it emphasizes is
progression we have to do certain types
of exercises in amounts and progression
strategies that continue to challenge it
which means it needs to continue to be
overloaded to continue to remodel and
add additional bone density those
osteocytes that we talked about earlier
the blasts and the class get
desensitized really quickly to the same
stimuli it's very very adaptable I said
earlier in the show that we tend to
think about bone is this kind of this
inert thing and it's not it's highly
highly plastic and it is paying
attention this desensitization happens
really quickly this is why things like
static loads and repetitive kind of low
magnitude loads are not osteogenic
Unfortunately they are great for lots of
things they're awesome but for bone
mineral density bone health specifically
they're just not very effective if
effective at all you have to emphasize
rather impact dependent things so so you
can impact the ground this is landing
jumping up and down and Landing you
could do tumbling like I guess you could
join a judo class or a Jiu-Jitsu or
gymnastics something where you're
landing and the impact is happening all
over the place the most common and and
where a lot of the research got started
here was actually in tennis players so
some of the original research on this
entire understanding of the role of
impact on boneal density came from
studies in which they looked and they
realized that you tennis players had way
more bow Minal density in the arm that
they hold their racket in and so you
think like really that tiny little
tennis ball that weighs a few
ounces well that was enough why because
it was happening rapidly right smashing
full
velocity that led to the significantly
different bone we see this all the time
in our pitchers and and different
athletes that have sort of asymmetrical
loading strategies so the ground can be
something that you impact it could be an
Implement again like a tennis racket
it could be simply faster pulling on the
bone so you're doing any exercise or
activity and it's requiring you to snap
and Pull and change directions or
whatever the case is as long as that's
being done aggressively then those
osteocytes are going to feel like
literally feel that on the bone and then
start adding to that Reformation or that
bone metabolism process so now that you
understand the concepts we're trying to
get after I thought it'd be helpful to
go over one very specific protocol what
I'm going to get into is What's called
the lift more randomized control control
trials this was all led by Belinda Beck
uh who's a Gulf Coast in Australia I
think but the lift more is l f m o r I
love when scientists come up with
awesome names for their control trials U
these originally came out in like 2017
2018 and I'm I'm not going to exaggerate
here by calling these
groundbreaking and that's because I
remember still as an undergraduate
graduate student being terrified
honestly of working with anybody older
because of Frailty concern
and that's because people would just
Hammer you they would really put the
fear of of Zeus in you that you're going
to break somebody's bones and so we were
terrified of having people lift weights
if they were unless we knew for a fact
that they had quality bones prior 2017
we had really very little evidence that
strength training was okay and safe for
people with osteoporosis and we had very
little evidence that was actually
beneficial until these lift more control
trials started coming out these lift
more trials there was a bunch of them
but the one I'm going to focus on right
now was I think the first one and it was
in postmenopausal women that had known
low bone mass right so they knew these
women were at risk they later repeated
it in men now the trial itself was 8
months long and what they did is they
looked at a uh what they called like a
higher intensity resistance and impact
training and they compared that to lower
impact training the higher impact
training was twice per week for 30
minutes and it was supervised I think it
was in the clinic okay and what they did
is they did five sets of five
repetitions at 85% of one rep max right
which is awesome you would generally
think what like you're when we think
exercise in in clinical populations we
always like you know three sets of 10 at
60% kind of thing they said no we're
taking people that we know are at you
know higher risk of fractures and Falls
we're doing 5x5 at 85 % four exercises I
think they did deadlift back squat um
overhead press and then the impact came
with this jumping chin up exercise so
the people stood kind of below the bar
they jumped up grabbed the chin-up bar
did a pull up or a chin up and then all
the way at the top let go fell all the
way back down to the ground and landed
so they were getting that plyometric uh
emphasis by by Landing there so those
four exercises took about 30 minutes the
other group did lower intensity stuff
like walking uh lunges they did front
raises and some other body weight
exercises and I think the highest they
let them get up to was 3 kilograms of
load so they did it at home they did low
air intensity stuff now there had been
enough studies done at this point that
you basically knew the lower intensity
was not going to work like we just
simply know walking doesn't do the trick
for bone maral density um 3 kilog is not
going to be
enough and then to kind of summarize
what found out was the the higher
intensity resistance impact training
stuff it basically won there was a lot
of measures taken there was a lot of
bone Minal density measures taken and
again basically all the metrics at I'm
exaggerating a little bit but most of
the metrics for bone Minal density
improved way more in the lifting and
Landing group than the low intensity
group strength got better so this was
really impactful because it answered two
really big questions arguably three one
you're not going to break people they if
done properly and supervised and there's
more detail to how they they warm people
up and like all that stuff's in the
paper right 5 by5 85% four big exercises
and these people didn't break bones
which in of itself was enough to to
shock many people number two it actually
was way more effective than the standard
exercise programs the third one I would
argue is this translated into other
things in life because their legs got
stronger their upand go time
sit to stand times these functional
activities of daily living metrics got
way better as well so translated into
other areas of their life which is
impactful
so since then it's been very hard to
argue
scientifically that lifting weights is
is dangerous or something you should
avoid for people with osteoporosis in
fact I think we can say pretty
definitively at this point it's a very
very good thing to do so if you're the
type of person who likes to listen to
podcast like this and they want an exact
number an exact routine you can go
follow the protocol that Belinda did in
her studies if you like things more
broadly if I were to summarize the whole
field this is what I'd say the bone
health exercise guidelines look like
this is everything from how frequent how
intense what exercises rest volume and
so on and so forth so starting us off
with intensity one thing that we know
has to happen is the intensity of
exercise has to be somewhere between
moderate to high that directly
influences our exercise Choice the
exercises have to be
weightbearing you generally want them to
be
multi-directional because the
adaptations are sight specific in other
words if you do nothing but upper body
Plyometrics so imagine doing like a
push-up and Landing with the push-up
you're not going to see any change in
your lumbar or your femur or your hips
in terms of boneal density the same is
true with the opposite if all you're
doing is Plyometrics your upper body
won't change its bone Ral density it is
site specific that is really clear from
the research so you want to do
multidirectional total body different
movement patterns frontal pattern
frontal plane sagittal plane uh
rotational movements like all kinds of
things like this right to get all
aspects of bone manal density high so we
got to be intense we got to load it and
we want to pick exercises uh that are
well-rounded in terms of how I'm getting
loaded and in the areas that I'm loading
it if you do that then all you want to
do is try to get as much stimuli on
there as much as you can what's that
mean
frequency can you give me two days a
week great can you give me four better
can you give me seven even better now
that's not the case for things like
muscle growth right but we're not trying
to do that right now if you want the
most amount of stimuli on the the bone
then stimulate it the most amount that
you possibly can so the more frequent
the better in terms of challenging the
bomb if you do those three things then
when it comes to volume and rest and
order you can do really whatever you
want as long as it doesn't compromise
the previous ones so here's what I mean
if you want to do a set of 50
repetitions and you want to take a 20
second break and do it again and your
heart rate gets really really high and
you get a lot of sweat going on is that
going to help bone moral
density probably not because what had to
happen with load you had to go light for
that right because you did a lot of reps
and you did High fatigue and so you
probably didn't get enough impacts to
stimulate the muscle growth this is not
a game of fatigue we're not talking
about fat loss we're not talking about
building your endurance or your
mitochondrial health or anything else
like that we got to make sure the
intensity and the loading are there so
as long as your
volume whether this is the amount of
repetitions per set the amount of sets
you're doing the rest anal you're taking
are not taking away from the things that
have to happen then you can really do
whatever you would like here the order
order of the exercises same thing it
doesn't matter bone doesn't care about
order not a big deal you got to be able
to progress which is our last modifiable
variable long as you can do that
everything else is entirely up to you
modify it how you see fit always
customize always individualize but make
sure you hit those previous Concepts and
you should be doing the best you can for
using exercise to stimulate bone growth
I love to continue on convincing you
that exercise specific is strength
training is awesome but I think you're
getting the point by now so I'm going to
move on to our next big category and
I'll consider these to be things that
are cheap or kind of medium price point
exercise is basically free in my opinion
so within this category I'm going to
first start off with nutrition and
supplements and there's a handful of
things we can talk about here but first
and foremost and the one that always
comes to mind is calcium now it makes
sense with what we talked about earlier
as long as your calcium intake is
sufficient and that should preserve it
in bone and yada y bone health should
stay a right so with that in mind it's
easy to have people think that taking a
calcium supplement will either preserve
bone health or stop it from declining in
the first place unfortunately it doesn't
really pan out like that the vast
majority of the time as long as you're
kind of hitting medium numbers something
like 800 to 1,000 milligrams of caffeine
or calcium rather per day you tend to be
fine adding a calcium supp on top of
that doesn't seem to have much of an
impact on overall bone health um now
this is another case where it's sort of
like if you're in the low end of the
spectrum so say you're in a position of
low food quality or you can't eat it or
a kid won't eat it or something like
that then going from low to normal there
might be a place but going from normal
to high in terms of calcian intake
doesn't seem to make much of an impact
you're probably just going to excrete
most of that back out now in terms of
like getting 800 to 1,000 Mig of of
calcium per day it's not particularly
hard biggest places you're going to get
them from most common ones are things
like yogurt cheese dairy products I
think the average glass of milk has like
300 milligrams so you know in in passing
with most people if you're eating
somewhat amounts of reasonable real food
you're you're probably going to get
somewhat close to that it's just a
threshold issue right so if you're
getting it in food you're okay you don't
need it if you're not getting it then
this is when supplements would turn to
be the case so I would differentiate the
impact of calcium supplements based upon
kids and adults most part adults don't
see much of an impact there um the data
are very mixed to not impressive kids if
it's low take it if not you should be
fine the next thing on our list is
actually surprising enough protein
there's a really cool paper that came
out uh quite uh it's actually been a few
years now I think 2019 um dietary
protein and bone health across the life
course it's an updated systematic review
and meta analysis over 40 years this one
actually catches people off guard a lot
they do not realize the impact protein
intake has on bone health that doesn't
seem to be a connection there they don't
understand why lots of different things
going be happening here but it may and I
emphasize May um enhance bone health by
improving calcium absorption um thing
called igf1 uh by increasing lean bone
mass or lean body mass itself and so
kind of these like secondary actions uh
tend to be the the most prominent
likelihood of why protein intake
helps with bone health um it also
accounts for some the neighbor like 2 to
4% of the overall variance in bone
mineral density so it's an impactful
thing but it is not nearly as impactful
as all the other stuff we've been
talking about thus far fish oil is
another supplement that I'll come up
really routinely it's honestly like a
pretty similar story here there's a lot
of really good research on animals some
stuff in human admittedly it's more
mixed some of them been really
impressive other ones have been saying
ah okay there's not much here it's
likely very dose and condition dependent
and and I think this theme will run
through of just about everything in this
category so you know what I mean when I
say that if they're really bad the
supplement helps if they're okay in this
area the supplement probably doesn't
have as much of an in fact but like
protein there's so many documented
benefits of fish oil it's just it's just
almost a no risk potential reward
scenario so why not now collagen is
another one
remember the bulk of your bone is made
of collagen uh been a lot of research
well more recent research on this stuff
um looking at things that are called
specific collagen peptides now we can
perhaps later you can Google what that
means but there have been randomized
control trials in women postmenopausal
women um that have looked at these
things and in general it seems to be
pretty positive right bone Mino density
in the spine specifically and for moral
neck uh increased significantly with
collagen intake and I think think this
I'm pretty sure this was actually done
at five grams of collagen per day that's
a really low amount if you were to get
collagen um I know specifically the one
that momentus makes momentus of course
is a sponsor of this show and I've long
been involved with that company
personally I think that their serving
size is 20 grams and so five grams is a
very very modest amount the fact that
they saw benefits in two very important
sites in bone Minal density with 5 GRS
uh per day of college is really really
impactful uh and I and I think
Monumental I haven't seen a ton of
follow-up studies on this I'm not
exactly sure why but you could dive into
the details uh of some of this research
and again I think you're going to be
more impressed this is another one that
like really surprises people they don't
realize these data are out there and the
the the magnitude of impact is really
impressive you're talking about like 4
to 7% increases in bone Minal density um
over a 12- month span right so again
they're doubling the length here so we
see more Improvement but as we've been
talking about um that that's quite a bit
so something I think certainly is worth
paying attention
to and considering again not a lot of
downside potentially You could argue
that the cost is a little bit high but
that's really it and has a a reasonable
chance to create some benefits here now
past this we've got to leave our comfort
zones of exercise lifestyle sleep and
nutrition right the next handful of
things I'm going to cover are things
like the stem cells biologics peptides
the gut microbiome I promised a little
bit earlier light therapies and so on
and so forth okay so let's get into what
we know about these and I'm going to hit
them all at a little bit of a high level
but this stuff is what I consider to be
whether you want to think about these as
second or third line options or just
more advanced because they're more
expensive they're less easy to get we
don't have as much detail on them but
enough quality evidence for me to bring
them up right now nonetheless let's
start off with what I'll call
Biologicals okay I'm going to cover stem
cells PRP peptides and growth factors
this is a really cool emerging area
there's a lot of talk always in the
biological space but what do we know
scientifically all right well when it
comes to Bone healing what we're now
talking about is folding in some of that
post bone break and how do I get it to
heal correctly and how do I get it to
heal faster do things like like stem
cells and PRP have a place in preserving
bone mass over time I don't know that's
a harder one to argue but if you do
break a bone can you use these things to
to come back faster probably right very
likely so here's what we know when a
bone breaks and it has to heal it's got
to go through three separate processes
inflammation repair and remodel we've
been talking about this repair remodel
all day so the step before that is the
inflammation and it turns out
the success of that inflammatory process
directly exp explains the success of the
bone healing if that inflammatory
process is not enough if you come in
with things like nids or cortical
steroids you block that inflammatory
process that will lead to worse bone
healing takes longer and it won't heal
as effectively you need that okay you
need that process because you have to
activate immune cells you have to
activate what are called mesenchimal
cells so these are called msc's we're
going to talk about these a little bit
later but that process has to happen or
bone doesn't heal correctly at the same
time if inflammation is excessive or so
bad because either things like uh what's
called poly trauma um this is an open
fracture where your bone broke and then
it opened up the skin you got an
infection or something like that like
additional trauma way too much
inflammation or you're in a state of
chronic
inflammation this is when we lead to
poor bone healing as well so we can
think about this and say okay a bone
broke what
happened if we can mitigate this
inflammatory process we can maximize our
bone healing and this is where these
Biologicals come into play so we'll
start off first with these stem cells or
msc's is the specific version we're
going to focus on really cool Recent
research has indicated that if you take
these MSC cells and you do what's called
preconditioning so you put them uh you
also see this as like activated or
primed okay so these primed MSC cells
which means you basically soak them in a
bath of inflammation um you can do this
with like hypoxia you can do this with
tnf Alpha is one of the most common ones
you can precondition them with you put
them in these pro-inflammatory
environments prior to putting them in
you then you inject them into you then
you see these massive and regulated
inflammatory responses which is helpful
okay now what they specifically do is
these msc's these preconditioned ms's as
well as what's called their exosomes
these things that kind of come after it
promote these osteogenic differentiation
into
osteoblasts fancy way of saying you can
create more
osteoblasts right so remember earlier
when I said hey you got to know what
growth and repair look like because the
interventions we work on tackle
different aspects of it this stuff is I
don't know if it's going to do much to
your Osteo class the red ones but it
does a lot for for the blast the B ones
on the back end right it also looks like
at this point that it may enhance Osteo
blast capacity so you're going to take
your immature or non-differentiated stem
cells and get them to differentiate to
creating more osteoblast and then making
the osto blast you have have greater
capacity if you paid attention to stem
cells at all you know that there's a
canyon worth of things we got to go
figure out how do we treat them how do
we dose them how do we store them all
those things are true here as well I
think in my opinion clearly there's
something there I can't tell you which
Clinic to go to I can't tell you which
one's the best because it's most of it
is unknown at this point but because we
know that these things can impact Osteo
blasts so well clearly there's something
there now a similar
one is PRP PRP has been around for a
long time platelet rich plasma um there
has been a lot of evidence actually for
many years on what we can do with PRP
Post bone fracture um and it's it's okay
I would say in general it's not the most
exciting Avenue we can go after probably
some other places that are of more
interest than PRP is maybe a nice way to
say it a more interesting area in my
opinion are peptides one of the more
common ones is called LP2 you'll see
that one pretty often um as always
because this area is emerging almost all
of the research is in animal models or
even basic cell culture and so the
numbers don't equivalate right so we see
there's like 15 X increases in bone
growth well in a cell or an animal
that's not going to translate into 15
15x increase in your bone health so
these are ones that we're pay attention
to um probably the ones that are the
most documented are what are called the
bmps these stand for bone morphogenic
proteins now the most common bmps are
BMP 2 4 and 7 all of them play a role in
bone but these ones are particularly
important for bone growth you'll see the
most evidence on bmp7 and two now bmp7
is not currently approved for human use
as far as I understand it um it's been
around for probably over 20 years but
it's it's not being used there
bmp2 is that's been approved for over 20
years now as far as I understand it it's
known to directly influence these Osteo
sites so the blasts and the class and
looks to be like 80 to 85% of the use is
off label meaning people are using mp2
for
non uh direct use you don't see this for
things like osteoporosis treatment now
this is why I'm bringing it up now where
you see this are traumatic bone breaks
so Physicians are using this to
accelerate that bone healing post break
not something that will impact bone
mineral density over the long period of
time that I'm aware of okay but what's
really cool about this is this field
sort of took off and then people took it
one step further and they said okay if
BMS are helpful what are impacting bmps
and so to make you Ultra confused
there's a whole subset of things that
are immature
peptides that come directly from most
specifically bmp7 so again the bmp7 is
not being used but the bmp7 derivatives
are the most popular and some of these
have bone forming Properties by far the
cheapest and smallest one is called bone
forming protein so we went from
bmps to
bfp if you're glancing across literat
you're going to get confused super fast
if you're not paying attention but what
you really need to understand is we
started off with the bmps bmp7 had a lot
of potential what's operating best
within bmp7 bfp and it started off with
bfp 1 then two and then even more
research on bfp 4 in fact there was a 20
21 Frontiers paper which is an excellent
high quality Journal found that b
fp4
outperformed the original
bmp7 and I would say is very clear at
this point most of the research in this
area has drilled in on these
bfps another potential option you want
to think about is physical heat again
we're not talking about saying hey if
you go sit in the sauna you'll reverse
your osteoporosis I I don't think that
that's the case and I'm certainly don't
have any information or evidence to
suggest that is what we're talking about
here is using heat applications directly
on Bones post break in a surgical uh
manifestation of it here there's
actually been plenty of research on this
and it seems to be very effective heat
stimulation enhances the osteogenic
capacity really clearly and there's a
lot of commercially available biom
materials that you can use ins surgeons
can use to put on bone post surgery
that's the general use case here one
study actually in particular Found Used
heat once a week they I think they did
15 minutes for a month at 45 degrees
Celsius or about 113 degrees Fahrenheit
depending on what you prefer so like
pretty hot there again not a whole body
exposure this is a direct bone exposure
and they saw significant increases in
bone mineralization and they even
directly found new bone forming from the
periphery and moving towards the center
there is additional information on this
temperature thing though and this is
actually where we're going to transition
and cross a couple of categories this
line of research is fascinating but
there is a lot of evidence that warmth
prevents bone
loss via the gut
microbiome that's right so warmth
physical temperature where you live at
on the earth how hot it is in your
climate will impact positively bone
health via the the gut microbiome so let
me walk you through that right now so
here's how that works there's a great
paper that we'll have full access to if
you want to go read it it's actually
open access for everyone to go download
on their own anyways but let me give you
a couple of highlights from that paper
first it's been generally shown that
people in warm exposures have improved
bone strength into adulthood and it also
seems to prevent osteoporosis in most
animal models so point of evidence
number one it seems to be if you live in
a warmer environment
bones tend to be better number two there
have been human meta analyses that show
inverse correlations between hip
fractures and temperatures now I know
that these are not randomized control
trials and when I say that for the
record what I mean is they haven't taken
people with osteoporosis moved them to
the equator for six years or two years
or whatever came back and looked at
their stuff inverse correlation just
seems to be hey when we look at people
who generally live in warmer climates
they seem to have better bones and lo
less osteoporosis than people who are in
colder climates right that's only
correlation and we know correlation is
not causation but we're starting to
build a bunch of evidence in the same
direction which it's just another piece
of evidence for our our overall mystery
we're trying to solve here right so
that's second thing to pay attention to
third one is there have been studies
that have looked at
transplantation of warm adapted
microbiome or
microbiota and that can prevent vent
bone loss here's what I
mean you can take an animal from a warm
temperature extract their gut microbiota
put it in another animal that animal
then the second animal will see
preventions in bone
loss and so something that was exposed
via the temperature in the original
animal caused some changes in the gut
microbiome that were then able to be
transplanted to another animal that
ultimately all the way preserved bone
loss in that secondary animal if that
doesn't demonstrate the impact and
important I don't know what other stuff
you can be looking for of course we want
to see it does it hold true in humans
may or may not but pretty awesome to
think about okay fourth thing here is
those other studies I just mentioned we
know that warmth direct heat application
enhances production of of polyamines and
things like that that increase bone
strength and so when you combine all
this literature together it's I I think
it's a pretty compelling story that
there is something here are we at the
End of This research line do we know all
the answers no but it's enough for me to
pay attention to and enough for me to
bring up in this podcast so you can
infer from that what you will if this
area fascinates you as much as it does
me you can do a couple of things one
just Google gut bone access and then see
all the papers that come up two there's
a couple of papers that will directly
link to in our show notes one of them is
called the brain gut axis a
neurodegenerative disease it's covers a
bunch of different stuff here another
one is called the microbiota bone axis
in aging related bone diseases and what
they're going to show in talk about a
little bit more that I just don't want
to get into right now are how what is a
direct connection what is being changed
what is being produced in the out of the
gut microbiome that's influencing things
like cortisol influencing estrogen
influencing
thyroid and mineral deposits like that
we know that's the mechanism right so
how it what's coming out of the gut
that's changing and altering behavior of
our class and our blast and these papers
will walk you through that the more we
start to learn about how these things
like short chain fatty acids regulate
inflammation um how when we modulate
these classs in these blasts and they
regulate with en enzymes like
tph1 um and 5ht which influence things
like serotonin of course Bol acids uh it
seems to be clearly pretty clear that
there's going to be a strong
relationship and then eventually likely
there'll be intervention steps we can
take for the gut microbiome and overall
bone health I want to move on now and
talk about the little bit of evidence we
have for things like light and photo
biomodulation now if you look into this
actually where I would turn your
attention to First is what's called low
intensity laser therapy or LL right A
lot of times we call this Cally in the
field cold laser these seem to work
there seems to be evidence there there's
not a ton of evidence we need more but
that seems to be a reasonable thing to
think about there is much more evidence
um on the pbms the
photobiomodulation if you want to think
about this as red light therapy you can
lots of stuff in the area of red light
for bone healing uh there's at least
eight studies that I'm aware of and
what's interesting is most of this comes
from the Dentistry world so whether this
translates into the rest of your bones I
I think will I think it should but I
can't say that definitively at this
point of the eight studies I pulled up
seven of the eight in humans found
improvements in healing with red light
therapy or photo biom modulation
frequency is everything from every day
to even like every other day um duration
generally you're looking at 10 to 20
minutes if you want to learn more about
that I I encourage you to check out the
links in our show notes and so that said
I'm going to move on and talk about one
of our last categories and that is what
I'll just call electricity and this is
everything from the e stimulation like
the Catalyst suits or other um various
things like the mark Pro unit I've used
in the past before for other things um
this could also be there's there's a
growing amount of research on
PF which you know people have been
talking about recently that's come up
and then there's even cool things like
electrically based Nanobots that are
being used and explored and that stuff
seems to be very prom promising okay so
one paper I would uh bring your
attention to is called focus on bone
healing new strategies for improvements
of bone
healing one more time this is probably
not for osteoporosis this is most likely
to be accelerating post broken bone
right um in general what you'll see is
electrical stimulation has pretty solid
potential I think that's fair to say um
but it is high cost right it is
inconvenient the results are admittedly
a little bit
inconsistent um and it's it's hard to
have a wide uh applicability right
getting into a pmf is cumbersome and
these are challenges but there's stuff
here right so you can take a look at at
the one specifically uh there's a
handful of papers that have been coming
out and I would anticipate more coming
out on
PF um and different electrical chemical
signals that we can put in the body but
I actually think that if I had to
predict something's going going to be
there eventually so we covered a lot of
ground in today's episode and if I could
summarize it I would say this number one
prevention is by far our biggest weapon
for bone health what this mostly means
is exercise human movement sports or
however you want to think about it and
high quality foods especially in and
during the puberty window and especially
in girls outside of that if you just
avoid the big seven modifiable things
that take away from bone health you're
probably in a pretty good spot okay as a
quick reminder those big seven are
environmental toxins various diseases
drugs
medications sedentary activity
malnutrition chronic stress and bad
sleep there are other things that can
contribute to it but these are the big
ones right if though for whatever reason
you missed the window on that and you
found yourself in a situation in which
your bone density is lower than you'd
like it is never too late the rate of
improvement is modest but it is
Meaningful if you put in a lot of work
and you're really focused and you got a
trainer or you started making all these
changes and then you got another scan a
year later and you only saw a 3%
Improvement that mattered that's what
we're looking for you should be happy
and static and excited about that 3%
Improvement it's unrealistic to expect
50 or 20 or 80% changes there so the
improvements are small but they matter a
ton in final conclusion here if I lost
you with some of the technical details
if you're sitting here thinking I just
listened to a couple of hours of this
show and all he really told me was make
sure I don't lose bone mineral density
when I'm a kid and then be active that's
fine I would just ask that we can share
this message and bring awareness as much
as we possibly can I love muscle I'm a
muscle guy I love performance I love
sports but bone never gets its due it
never gets the emphasis that it needs
and it arguably impacts more people than
any of the stuff that I'm more
passionate about so spread awareness
have people think about it have people
get tested or at least start talking
about it and thinking about it and doing
the best they can with whatever
limitations that they have whatever
they're willing to do capable of doing
and have access to if we can start
making an impact on bone health we're
going to impact all of our lives for a
long long time thank you for joining for
today's episode my goal as always is to
share exciting scientific insights that
help you perform at your best if the
show resonates with you and you want to
help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world there are a few ways that you can
support first you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube Spotify and apple and on
Apple and Spotify you can leave us up to
a five-star review subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot also please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they're exceptional products and
services finally you can share today's
episode with a friend who you think
would enjoy it if you have any content
questions or suggestions please put
those in the comment section on YouTube
I really do try my best to read them all
and to see what you have to say I use my
Instagram and X profiles also
exclusively for scientific communication
so those are great places to follow
along for more learning my handle is Dr
Andy Galpin on both platforms we also
have an email newsletter that distills
all of our episodes in the most
actionable takeaways we have newsletters
on how to improve Fitness in You2 Max
how to build muscle and strength and
much more to subscribe to the newsletter
just go to perform podcast.com and click
newsletter it's completely free and we
do not share your email with anybody
thank you for listening and never forget
in the famous words of Bill Bowerman if
you have a body you are an athlete